Guide to the Ettie Crystal Riddell Papers, 1886-1968
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Ettie Crystal Riddell papers 1886-1968
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Riddell, Ettie Crystal, 1878-1968.
10 linear feet Extent: 2733 Items
Active in Disciples of Christ in Tennessee, Pennsylvania, and other states. Husband, Louis Riddell, was a minister for the denomination. Collection contains correspondence, diaries, notebooks, scrapbooks, photographs, and other materials relating to Riddell and her husband, Louis Riddell. The materials document not only Riddell's personal life as the wife of a minister and her involvement in the Disciples of Christ ministry, but also the evolving role of women in American religious communities. Notebooks contain sermons that Ettie Riddell delivered to women's groups. Her diaries date chiefly from the 1930s to the 1960s, but there are also two early diaries from 1894 and 1896. Other materials, especially correspondence, clippings, and sermon notes, document the ministry of Louis Riddell and the lives of other Riddell family members.
riddellettie
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Ettie Crystal Riddell Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1993-1997.
Biographical Note
Ettie Crystal Riddell (1878-1968) was active in the Disciples of Christ in Tennessee, Pennsylvania, and other states. Her husband, Louis Riddell, was a minister for the denomination.
Collection Overview
Collection contains correspondence, diaries, notebooks, scrapbooks, photographs, and other materials relating to Riddell and her husband, Louis Riddell. The materials document not only Riddell's personal life as the wife of a minister and her involvement in the Disciples of Christ ministry, but also the evolving role of women in American religious communities. Notebooks contain sermons that Ettie Riddell delivered to women's groups. Her diaries date chiefly from the 1930s to the 1960s, but there are also two early diaries from 1894 and 1896. Other materials, especially correspondence, clippings, and sermon notes, document the ministry of Louis Riddell and the lives of other Riddell family members.
A large number of the materials are annotated by Dorothy S. Bruce (now Welbon), granddaughter of Ettie Crystal Riddell and Louis D. Riddell. The materials are in original order as received; basic processing but no rearrangement was performed. Container list was created by the donor.
The list includes notations for ECR (Ettie Crystal Riddell) and LDR (Louis D. Riddell).
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Riddell, Ettie Crystal; Riddell, Louis; Riddell family; Disciples of Christ -- Clergy; Disciples of Christ -- Sermons; Disciples of Christ -- Tennessee; Disciples of Christ -- Pennsylvania; Women -- Religious life -- United States; Women in Christianity -- United States; Women -- Southern States -- Diaries; Sermons; Tennessee -- Religious life and customs; Pennsylvania -- Religious life and customs; Diaries; Scrapbooks; Clippings; Photographs; Sermons
Detailed Description of Collection
- Container List, (16 boxes; 1 oversize folder)
  - ECR diaries, 1934, 1936-1945 (Box 1)
  - ECR diaries, 1946-1953 (Box 2)
  - ECR diaries, 1954-1959 (Box 3)
  - Box of approximately 40 postcards from ECR, LDR, family, and friends, 1907-1909, 1920s-1940s
  - Manuscript and printed copy of Reminiscence, 1941
    Poem written by ECR for church bulletin (January 26, 1941) on the occasion of the end of Louis D. Riddell's pastorate at the North Street Christian Church in Butler, Penn., which was from March 4, 1920 to January 26, 1941.
  - Two letters from Katherine Clifford van Arsdall, first female graduate of Kentucky University, 1898 and 1908
  - ECR's handwritten description of LDR's early childhood
  - Notebook with notes, quotes, clippings, photos, poems, and prayers, undated
    One poem is by Helen Riddell, ECR and LDR's child who died in 1928 at age 11.
  - Disciples and the Church Universal, by Robert O. Fife, published by Disciples of Christ Historical Society, Nashville, Tenn.
  - ECR diaries, 1960-1963, 1965 (Box 4)
  - Memorial book from ECR's funeral service
  - Prayer, meditation, and history of Howard and Chariton Counties, 1893, by James M. Riddell (father of LDR)
  - Photocopies of notes by LDR and ECR
  - Letters to Pension Fund, 1947, 1957, 1961
  - Notes from Chautauqua
  - Riddell family history booklet, with photos and news clippings, including Helen Riddell's obituary, 1928 (Box 5)
  - Sermon notes by LDR, 1924, 1938, 1946-1947
  - Membership and financial records for the Disciples of Christ Church, Butler, Penn., 1940s
  - History of Rothville Christian Church, Missouri, 1924
  - Booklet with biography of LDR
  - Photograph of McLenmore Ave. Church, Memphis
  - Wedding ceremony used by LDR
  - Impressions from a Trip to Europe, and a poem, America for Me, by Henry Van Dyke
  - Funeral service for Martha Shriver, 1939
  - Sermon notes from the last service LDR preached, November 24, 1946
  - Sermon notes and outlines by LDR
  - Prayers by LDR
  - Butler, Penn., high school graduation sermon by LDR, 1939
  - News clippings about LDR sermon at Mississippi Ave. church, pre-1909
  - Valentines received by LDR as a child
  - Piano recital program, 1915
  - Centennial announcement of Christian Church, 1809-1909 in the Endeaver Evangel
  - LDR notebook of expenses and addresses, 1893
  - Miscellaneous notes and prayers, 1899
  - Poem by ECR, 1891
  - Letters between LDR and ECR, 1894-1899, 1901-1903
  - ECR expenditures, 1905, 1907
  - Letter from Ethel (daughter of ECR and LDR) to ECR's brother, 1909
  - Letter from LDR after his father's funeral, 1910
  - Photograph of Virgie, ECR's sister, 1894
  - Photograph of Riddell family, Springfield, Tenn., circa 1897
  - LDR Reward of Merit card, circa 1880
  - Christmas card from Grace Toof
  - Nineteenth Century Club booklet, 1890
  - Family photographs, 1896-1912
  - The Story of My Life booklet by ECR for daughter Ethel, 1907
  - ECR trip notes, 1911
  - Ethel report card and records, 1912-1916
  - Letters between Riddell family, 1915
  - Letters from young men's class, 1914
  - Piano recital program, 1912
  - Incoming letters from Ethel and other family members to ECR and LDR, 1919-1927
  - Correspondence, ECR, 1928-1931 (Box 6)
  - Women's Club of Butler Spring Luncheon program, 1932
  - Correspondence, 1964-1936
  - Birth announcement for Judith Carol Smith, 1938
  - Correspondence, 1938-1944
  - Postcards from Florida, undated
  - Correspondence, 1945
  - List of ECR and LDR Golden Wedding anniversary gifts, 1946
  - Letters from ECR and LDR to Ethel, 1946
  - Telegrams and lists of flowers from LDR's death, 1947
  - Correspondence and condolences, 1947
  - LDR checkbook record, 1947
  - LDR obituary, 1947
  - Correspondence, 1948-1954
  - Correspondence, 1955-1964 (Box 7)
  - Tribute to ECR from her young men's class, with 1912 program from Loyal Sons banquet, 1964
  - Church bulletin with poem by ECR, 1966
  - Letter to ECR just prior to her death, from B.D. Phillips, 1967
  - Items from ECR's death and funeral, 1967
  - Photograph of Riddell family in Rothville, undated
  - Photograph of ECR's class at Kentucky University, 1894
  - ECR diary, 1964
  - "Sunbonnet" girl postcards depicting traditional duties for the days of the week
  - Notebooks with Ethel's school notes
  - Writing tablet with notes by ECR on life and civilization
  - Notebook with thoughts by ECR
  - Folder with material on the sale of a farm and identification of various family members and friends by Dorothy Bruce
  - Original 1894a diary
  - Original 1894b diary
  - Photocopy of 1894 diaries
  - Typed copy of 1894 diaries
  - Original 1896 diary
  - Typed copy of 1896 diary
  - ECR notes on her childhood and reflections on her life, 1931 (Box 8)
  - Congenial Study Club talk notes and draft by ECR, 1964
  - A Perfect Tribute, about Abraham Lincoln, by Mary Raymond Shipman Andrews, 1922
  - "A Vision of the Future," paper read by ECR at Christian Women's Board of Missions' 50th anniversary
  - Student Handbook, Brenau College, 1942-1943
  - Wednesday Morning Music Club booklet, 1930-1931
  - Letters between Dorothy and Disciples of Christ Historical Society, 1990s
  - Photo album, inscribed McLenore Avenue Junior Endeavor Society, Memphis, 1911
  - Speech, B.B. Taylor on Christian Union, 1886
  - Clippings and notes by LDR on Christian Evangelist, 1896
  - Photograph of LDR and his Kentucky University classmates, 1898
  - Speeches, letters, and papers by ECR, 1930s and undated
  - Biographies and articles on church men
  - Recital programs from Teachers College, Columbia University, 1920s
  - Prayer, undated
  - Photographs of ECR's father, George W. Crystal, undated
  - Letter to ECR from J.T. Wheeler about the death of her father, 1934
  - Notebook with ECR's notes and expenses from a road trip, 1936
  - ECR speech notes, 1960
  - Correspondence, 1915-1922
  - ECR speech, A Minister's Wife Looks at the Pulpit, given to the Ministerial Association of Pittsburgh, 1944
  - Alone with God, given to LDR by his mother, 1891
  - Postcards and photographs
  - Church directory and bulletins, 1900s
  - News clipping about LDR leaving McLemore Avenue church, 1912
  - Telegram to LDR asking him to be state secretary, 1923
  - Loyal Sons Bible Class banquet program, 1912
  - Church activities new clippings
  - List of gifts to Ethel when her child died
  - Various poems, programs, stories, and lyrics
  - Photographs of Pike's Peak bought by ECR and LDR on their honeymoon, 1896
  - Photographs and Christmas cards from Phillips Hall
  - Closing speech of Carlos P. Romulo, from Philippines Delegation to the Asian American conference, 1955
  - Letters to ECR from L.G. Certhic, Asst. Secretary for Educational Services, 1961
  - Postcards and cards, 1902-1910 (Box 9)
  - McLenore Avenue Christian Church bulletins, 1909
  - Notes from ECR
  - 9 Letters from brother of Virginia Deane (ECR's mother), who was stationed at Camp Douglas and Lake Village, Ark., 1860-1865
  - Letters to Mattie Deane (ECR's aunt), 1871-1902
  - Issue of The Delineator: The Woman's Favorite Magazine, with fabric swatch marking ECR's wedding dress pattern, 1896
  - ECR speeches and columns
  - Guestbook for ECR and LDR's Golden Wedding anniversary, 1946, with insertions, 1919-1956
  - Notebook with notes on developing a trained Christian young womanhood, 1929
  - Family history blank book, filled in by LDR
  - Genealogical notes, news clippings, and announcements
  - Notebook with clippings, photos, notes on Christian marriage, 1959 (Box 10)
  - Notebook by ECR, 1964
  - Copy of sermon by R.B. Willis, 1912
  - Sesquicentennial issue of Crimson Rambler, 1930
  - Transylvania College Bulletin, 1947
  - Correspondence between ECR and Anna Belle Hamilton, 1939-1959
  - Correspondence between ECR and Anna Belle Hamilton, 1960-1968 (Box 11)
  - Correspondence between ECR, LDR, and friends and family, 1907-1957
  - Photographs of ECR and LDR, 1941
  - Miscellaneous invitations, news clippings, and notes, 1920s-1940s
  - Programs, bulletins, and clippings from various church events, 1900s (Box 12)
  - Photograph of Hambletts, 1903
  - Letters, 1985-1986
  - The Minister's Wife, clipping, 1924
  - Miscellaneous materials: recipes, calling cards, cards, bulletins, notes, verses, etc.
  - New clippings from LDR's career, church history, and doctrine
  - Notebook with ECR speech to Missionary society on responsibilities of Christian womanhood in relation to world events, 1939
  - Immensee reprint, Theodore Storm, in German (Box 13)
  - ECR diary photocopies, 1894
  - Photographs of Europe trips, 1927
  - Photographs of Grace Riddell in college
  - Photocopies of news clippings, 1896-1941 of LDR and church news
  - LDR diplomas from Normal School and Kentucky University (Box 14)
  - Clippings saved by ECR
  - Photographs churches and church groups
  - Photographs from ECR and LDR last trip to Florida
  - Four scrapbooks with various news clippings, music, photos, bulletins, letters, 1896 wedding announcement for ECR and LDR (Box 15-16)
  - The Christian Guide, Nov. 8, 1895 (Oversize-box 21)